Guide to the Stephen Haweis Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Stephen Haweis Papers,
1860-1969
Haweis, Stephen.
5 linear ft. (ca. 1,300 items in 15 boxes & 4 oversize folders)
Columbia University, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078458
Biographical Note
Stephen Haweis (1878-1969), youngest son of the Reverend Hugh Reginald and Mary Eliza Haweis, a socially prominent couple in late Victorian London who entertained at their house in Cheyne Walk (previously owned by Dante Gabrielle Rossetti). Stephen studied art in Paris with Alphonse Mucha and Eugene Carrière. After becoming interested in photography, Stephen met Rodin and subsequently photographed many of the sculptor's pieces. In 1903 he married the poet Mina Loy (they were divorced in 1917). After losing much of his inheritance in the stock market crash of 1929, Stephen moved to the West Indian island of Dominica, where he studied and painted tropical fish, wrote for local newspapers, and worked on a variety of writing projects till his death.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, artwork, objects, and printed material. Included among the list of 37 cataloged correspondents are: Vera Brittain, Edward Gordon Craig, Clarence Darrow, Havelock Ellis, Augustus John, Emmeline Pankhurst, Edward Steichen, Gertrude Stein, Algernon Charles Swinburne, Sybil Thorndike, Alec Waugh, and H. G. Wells. The cataloged manuscripts include a poem by Witter Bynner entitled "Hay Wagon." There is a large selection of Stephen's writings (poetry, novels, plays, articles, biographies, memoirs) including drafts of a proposed biography of his father, a bound volume of his own memoirs, numerous notebooks, and "Mount Joy," a description of life on Dominica. His photographs and paintings are well represented, with 6 albums of photographs and 2 boxes & 1 folder of approximately 200 paintings and sketches. The printed material includes works by Stephen, his father and his mother.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Cataloged Series
Series II: Arranged Series
Arrangement
Cataloged correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and artwork (Box 1); Arranged correspondence (Box 2); Arranged manuscripts (Boxes 3-10); Arranged documents, photographs, and objects (Box 11); Printed materials (Boxes 12 & 13); Artwork by Stephen Haweis (Box 14 & 15 & oversize folders)
Subjects
Brittain, Vera, 1893-1970.; Bynner, Witter, 1881-1968.; Craig, Edward Gordon, 1872-1966.; Darrow, Clarence, 1857-1938.; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939.; John, Augustus, 1878-1961.; Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1858-1928.; Steichen, Edward, 1879-1973.; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946.; Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909.; Thorndike, Sybil, Dame, 1882-1976.; Waugh, Alec, 1898-1981.; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946.; Painters--England--Dominica--20th century.; Albums.; Articles.; Biographies.; Diaries.; Memoirs.; Microfilms.; Notebooks.; Novels.; Paintings.; Photographs.; Plays.; Poems.; Sketches; Artists.; Authors, English.; Journalists.; Painters
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
07/20/1988 M-88-07-20 Roosevelt, Mrs. Philip J Gift of the Estate
09/--/1994 94-09 Microfilm of memoir, 8 p. Added
08/--/1994 M-94-8 5 oil paintings Roosevelt, Mrs John Gift
Alternate Formats
Haweis' memoirs (28 p. bound volume) are on microfilm.
Gift of the Estate of Mrs. Philip J. Roosevelt, 1988.
Gift of Mrs. John Roosevelt, 1994.
- Series I: Cataloged Series
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence
    - Barnes, Sir Kenneth Ralph, 1878- (Box 1)
    - Beebe, William (Box 1)
    - Brittain, Vera, 1893-1970 (Box 1)
    - Carlton, John Dudley, 1908- (Box 1)
    - Caroe, William Douglas, 1857-1938 (Box 1)
    - Craig, Edward Gordon, 1872 (Box 1)
    - Darrow, Clarence, 1875-1938 (Box 1)
    - Ellis, Alexander John (Box 1)
    - Ellis, Havelock (Box 1)
    - Galton, Francis, 1822-1911 (Box 1)
    - Geddes, Sir Patrick (Box 1)
    - Gogh-Bonger, Johanna van, 1862-1925 (Box 1)
    - Haweis, Hugh Reginald, 1838-1901 (Box 1)
    - Hawkins, Edwards Comerford (Box 1)
    - Hind, Charles Lewis, 1862-1927 (Box 1)
    - Hitchens, Ivon (Box 1)
    - Hodge, W. H. (Walter Henricks), 1912- (Box 1)
    - Huxley, Elspeth Joscelin, 1907 (Box 1)
    - John, Augustus Edwin (Box 1)
    - Johnston, Sir Reginald Fleming, 1874-1938 (Box 1)
    - Kelly, Sir Gerald Festus, 1879-1972 (Box 1)
    - Konody, P. G. (Box 1)
    - Lavery, John, 1856-1941 (Box 1)
    - Le Braz, Anatole (Box 1)
    - Mann, William M. (Box 1)
    - Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1858-1928 (Box 1)
    - Sandwich, George Charles Montagu, 9th Earl of, 1874- (Box 1)
    - Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966 (Box 1)
    - Seifriz, William 1888- (Box 1)
    - Somerset, Lady Isabella Caroline, 1851-1921 (Box 1)
    - Steichen, Edward (Box 1)
    - Stein, Gertrude (Box 1)
    - Swinburne, Algernon Charles (Box 1)
    - Taylor, Fred, 1875-1963 (Box 1)
    - Thorndike, Sybil (Box 1)
    - Waugh, Alec, 1898- (Box 1)
    - Wells, Herbert George, 1866-1946 (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Manuscripts
    - Bynner, Witter, 1881-1968 (Box 1)
    - Warner, Charles, 1846-1909 (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.3: Photographs and Art
    - Craig, Edwrad Gordon, 1872- (Box 1)
    - Joy, Thomas Musgrave, 1812-1866 (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Series
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence
    - Chipman, Renee (Box 2)
    - Haweis, Lionel (Box 2)
    - Haweis, Mary Eliza (Box 2)
    - Haweis, Stephen (Box 2)
    - Paynter, Thomas (Box 2)
    - Roosevelt, John E. (Box 2)
    - Torrey, Margaret E. (Box 2)
    - A-Z, (21 folders) (Box 2)
  - Subseries II.2: Manuscripts
    - Haweis, Hugh Reginald. Ink presses (Box 3)
    - Haweis, Hugh Reginald Notes (Box 3)
    - Haweis, Lionel Story of Deed of Gift (Box 3)
    - Haweis, Mary Eliza Chaucer Calendar (Box 3)
      On Microfilm: MN# 2001-3108-1
    - Haweis, Mary Eliza Diary (Box 3)
      On Microfilm: MN#2001-3108-1
    - Haweis, Mary Eliza Fragments (Box 3)
    - Haweis, Stephen Address book (Box 3)
    - Haweis, Stephen Memoir, (1 volume, 3 folders.) (Box 3)
    - Haweis, Stephen Notes for his Will (Box 3)
    - Mss Fragments, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Howe, Bea List of people painted by Thomas Musgrave Joy (Box 10)
      [With article.]
    - Paynter, Thomas [Paynter] family pedigree (Box 10)
    - Roosevelt, Mrs. John Story of the Stephen Haweis materials (Box 10)
  - Subseries II.3: Fiction
    - Short stories, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - Albut and the Old Man, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - The Archer of Living Eden (Box 4)
    - From Kalymnos He Came (Box 4)
      [Box 5]
    - A Great Lady, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Love Letters to Dead Ladies (Box 5)
    - Roseau in Dominica (Box 5)
    - The Satyr, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - The Scented East, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - The Secret Island (Box 5)
      [Box 6]
    - That Foolish Game (Box 6)
    - Treasure Trove, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Subseries II.4: Non-fiction
    - Bimonadism (Box 6)
    - The Daphne Affair (Box 6)
    - David Without Devotion (Box 6)
    - Death and All That, (3 volumes ) (Box 6)
    - Ezra Did It (Box 6)
    - Freedom on Quick Sand, (2 volumes ) (Box 6)
    - The Future and Imagination (Box 6)
      [Box 7]
    - Men and Women and Mortality and Morality (Box 7)
    - Mount Joy, (5 folders) (Box 7)
    - The Natural Way to Draw (Box 7)
      [Box 8]
    - Spoilt Child: the Story of Hugh Reginald Haweis, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - The Thirteenth Disciple (Box 8)
  - Subseries II.5: Notebooks
    - Notebooks, 1946-48 (Box 8)
    - Notebooks, ca. l948 (Box 8)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1949 (Box 8)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1950-67 (Box 8)
      [Box 9]
    - Notebooks, ca. 1952-65 (Box 9)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1963 (Box 9)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1964 (Box 9)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1967 (Box 9)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1967-69 (Box 9)
    - Notebooks, ca. 1968, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Subseries II.6: Plays
    - Because I love You (Box 9)
    - Clockwise (Box 9)
    - A House Set in Disorder (Box 9)
    - Pegs (Box 9)
    - They Hated Their Parents (Box 9)
    - The Three Hairs (Box 9)
    - [Untitled] (Box 9)
  - Subseries II.7: Poems
    - Miscellaneous poems by Stephen Haweis, (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - Poetry notebooks, (13 volumes) (Box 10)
  - Subseries II.8: Documents
    - Haweis, Stephen Patent for a musical instrument (Box 11)
    - Mrs. Stephens Statement by re Hugh Reginald Haweis (Box 11)
  - Subseries II.9: Photographs
    - Photograph albums, (6 volumes) (Box 11)
    - Photographs (loose) (Box 11)
  - Subseries II.10: Objects
    - Joy ,Thomas William Musgrave. Shell and hair (Box 11)
  - Subseries II.11: Printed Materials
    - Books by Stephen, his father, and his mother; exhibition; exhibition catalogs; clippings; and The Arbiter of Elegance by Bea Howe, the biography of his mother (Box 12 & 13)
  - Subseries II.12: Artwork
    - Haweis, Stephen Various pieces of original art (With an 11 page inventory by Margaret E Torrey), (ca. 200 items ) (Box 301)
      [Oversize boxes shelved with collection]